All right.
And should be good to go.
Well, thank you, Johnny.
Good morning, everyone.
My name is Porto Gonzalez and the program
managers for the medical psilocybin
program Welcome and good morning.
We're here with Ian Dunn,
who is the Chair of the Dosage
Administration and Clinical Practice
Committee,
but also the Chair of the Medical
Psilocybin Advisory Board.
So I just, I just put a message in a chat.
Please remember that this meeting is
being recorded and to keep language
appropriate as the recordings are made
public on the website.
We have the cameras off and that is
because we same thing with language.
We in case there is something that may be
inappropriate for the background,
we have turned off all cameras,
but we will open the mics for folks when
you are ready to speak.
And with that,
we'll have Ian start the meeting.
Ian, good morning, everyone.
Welcome to the Dosage Administration and
Clinical Practice Committee.
Today we're going to be going over
preparation and administration sessions,
bringing together what we had discussed
last time.
Last meeting we distinguished the
different clinical roles and this would
be the application of those different
clinical roles.
If what he would like to bring up the
preparation sessions while we would begin
with introductions,
if you would like to participate in
today's meeting,
just a brief statement about your name,
who you are, your any affiliations.
But if you would like to participate,
please raise your hand at this time.
All right.
And first up,
we've got Lori Golzar and Lori,
I have enabled your mic.
Thank you.
Hi.
Good morning.
Thanks for being here.
I'm Lori.
I live in Farmington, NM,
I'm a FNP and APMHNP and I work full time
for Centacor Foundation,
a substance use disorder facility.
And I also have a psychiatric clinic
there where I see outpatients as well in
the community.
So yeah, thank you so much for being here.
Appreciate it.
We are hopeful to present this to our
organization in Texas so that we can
potentially provide psilocybin therapy at
our facility here in Farmington.
This is just a thought and we are
bringing it forward to them.
So I'm hopeful to get as much information
as I can.
Appreciate it.
Awesome, thanks.
And let's see next we've got Chris
Peskowski and your mic is enabled.
Good morning, everybody.
Chris Peskowski, Advisory Board member,
just happy to be here.
Awesome.
Thanks, Chris.
And next got Don Moser and your mic is
enabled.
Hi, Don Moser, and I live in Las Vegas,
NM,
and I'm here to learn as much as possible.
Thank you so much for all your work.
Awesome.
Thanks, Don.
And next, we've got Cassandra Veeton.
Let's see.
And your mic is enabled.
Oh, I'm sorry to to unmute.
I'll still want to go.
Yeah, there.
Yeah.
Great.
I'm Cassandra Veeton.
I'm a psychologist.
I live half time in Lamey,
New Mexico and half time in San Diego.
And I'm a Co founder and clinical
psychology director at the Center for
Psychedelic Research at UC San Diego.
Awesome.
Thank you.
And next,
we've got Brenda Burgard and I have
enabled your mic.
Good morning, everyone.
I'm Brenda Burgard.
I am Chair for Training and Education for
the DoH here for psilocybin.
Thank you and I hope we have a great
meeting this morning.
Awesome.
Thanks, Brenda.
And next, we've got Jessica Eden.
And Jessica, I've enabled your mic.
Hello, my name is Jessica Eden.
I am a licensed clinical social worker in
New Mexico and Colorado and also a
licensed clinical facilitator in Colorado.
And so I've been working with
psychedelics and psilocybin specifically
for about the last four years.
And so I'm just here to participate and
learn.
Thank you.
Awesome.
Thanks, Jessica.
And looks like that was the last hand I
saw up, so we'll send it back to you.
Ian.
Perfect.
So in the last meeting we had talked
about the differentiation between
psychological preparation and
administrative preparation.
So just try and kind of get into the
guidance of those differences.
This document would kind of help to
specialize which one would be doing which.
As a reminder,
a psychedelic therapist is the more
holistic model,
whereas a bullet facilitator is generally
the person that is with them during
administration.
Generally doesn't have to be separately
credentialed outside of the Department of
Health.
Whereas the psychedelic therapist is
generally already a licensed healthcare
provider.
So let's get into the psychological
preparation.
So the psychedel,
the psychedelic therapist must be
involved in the psychological preparation
process to establish the clinical
foundation for treatment.
So they established the timing.
This phase must occur first to allow the
therapist to determine medical
appropriateness and approve or to firm
participation based on safety.
Clinical assessment.
The therapist conducts A comprehensive
biopsychosocial assessment and reviews
medical,
including medication interactions and
contraindications,
mental health and substance abuse history,
intention and setting.
Intention, setting, and object objectives.
The The therapist facilitates the
discussion of patient goals, intentions,
and expectations for the session to
establish a psychological framework for
the experience.
Orientation to set.
The therapist addresses the patient's
physical, emotional,
and psychological readiness,
helping them navigate set factors and
potential psychological changes.
Clinical safety planning.
This is where they would evaluate risk
for adverse responses,
create a formal safety plan and perform
an assessment of the patient support
system.
In terms of cultural and spiritual
alignment,
we would use trauma informed and
culturally competent communication.
The therapist ensures alignment regarding
any ceremonial,
cultural or spiritual elements that may
be present.
Dosing and tearing.
During this phase,
the therapist assigns the clinical
support tier and establishes dosing
parameters or considerations.
If a patient is determined to be
clinically inappropriate,
the therapist is responsible for
referring them to a primary care provider
or other appropriate treatment.
Ave.
So that would be kind of the
psychological preparation,
what we're wanting them to do beforehand.
In terms of administrative preparation,
this would be primarily done by the
facilitator in order to ensure you know
the proper personality fit when you are
going to be with this person,
maybe not next to them 24/7,
but just they're gonna be the presence to
ground you if you do have an adverse
reaction.
So we want to have them obtain and
document informed consent during the
session.
This will happen after the psychological
preparation.
This session is a primary opportunity for
the patient and facilitator to ensure the
report is good enough to fit the patient
goals.
This phase includes establishing
boundaries such as touch provinces,
providing written disclosures and are
orienting the patient to non scope,
non clinical scope of the facilitator.
The facilitator orients the patient to
the physical environment where the
session will occur.
This includes reviewing environmental
conditions, the lighting, the temperature,
the sound,
explaining privacy measures and ensuring
the patient is comfortable with the
facility layout.
The facilitators are responsible for
knowing how to escalate medical or
psychological concerns to the psychedelic
therapist or emergency services.
You know,
depending on what the specific adverse
event is.
And this should be part of their
orientation and they should provide the
materials for the patient self
administration in accordance with the
therapist direction.
Some combined timing and compliance
standards.
This is still up in pretty up in the air.
Patient shall complete at least two
preparation sessions totalling no less
than three hours prior to administration.
At least one session must be dedicated to
psychological preparation.
At least one session to administrative
preparation.
Where feasible,
at least one hour of total preparation
time shall be conducted in person.
Psychological preparation must be
completed and clinical appropriateness
determined before the final
administrative preparation session is
concluded.
And all activities,
including clinical screening results from
the therapist and informed consent from
the facilitator must be documented in the
patient record.
So now I'll open to any discussion,
questions, comments,
concerns on the preparation sessions.
All right.
And Lori, I see your hand up.
You can unmute when you're ready.
Thank you.
Hi, just a couple questions.
1 is you refer to the therapist but say
it has to be a a licensed clinical role.
So are is this like a provider like
either a doctor of psychology or a PMHNP
or psychiatrist in this?
I'm just want to make sure I understand.
Or is could this be any licensed
therapist that could be considered
therapist?
Psychological therapist please?
Generally it would be a therapist with
additional training on specific
assessment and general psychedelic
assessment.
This committee in the past has found that
most medical institutions don't teach
about psilocybin use.
So we would have to provide that
education ourselves anyway.
And that's why we had opened it up
originally to social workers or clinical
counselors or PhDs who may have who are
going to have additional training with
the program.
OK.
So they don't have to have a medical
background specifically.
I mean,
I I understand we all have to go through
the training anyhow.
Like Doctor Fatima or see me.
I don't remember how to say it.
I know she has like a conscious physician
program to teach providers, do they?
So they don't have to be medical
providers to be a psychedelic therapist
at this time.
No.
OK, Thank you.
Right.
And Chris?
You know,
I'm curious what happened to the document
we were working off of last time,
but this was the new document that sent
out.
The document we were working on last time
was just the clinical roles.
We had a preparation document that we
were working from.
Yeah.
So that one was based on before we had
done the clinical roles.
And at the last meeting we I had sent out
an additional copy of a new preparation
based on the updated definitions of the
roles because the the past one had the
facilitator doing everything.
And in the last meeting we had discussed
the difference between psychological and
administrative preparation.
All right.
I just, I think it's a,
a little bit frustrating that we have new
documents every time.
Like it kind of dishonours the process
that we're,
we were working on all of that stuff and
now we're, we're starting new, right.
But the previous document didn't bring up
the concerns of the separation of
psychological and administrative
preparation, which was brought up.
And then at the end of the last meeting,
I had let people know, well,
these definitions no longer apply,
so we're gonna go ahead and generate a
new one.
I had it sent out last week to be
reviewed and then now we're here.
So I, I think we also talked about,
you know, based on the clinical,
it's here that people fall into that a
lot of this work could be done by the
facilitator if it's not complex cases.
I think this is very restrictive.
And is there any, I mean,
the psychological preparation,
administrative preparation, I get the,
the difference of that,
but I don't know that that's like
necessarily has to be a split roles like
this.
And you know, the,
the people that are sitting should kind
of be involved in this whole process,
especially the cultural spiritual
alignment section.
I think if we're going to split this up
like this needs to be in the facilitator
part.
All right.
I'm fine with that.
The cultural and spiritual alignment.
Can I talk again please?
Yeah.
So as far as like the clinical assessment
part goes,
doesn't that need to be by a medical
provider of some capacity?
We had in the previous meeting,
I know we had discussed that they will be
meeting with like a psychiatric provider
or someone like that prior to determining
that this would be a good,
a good therapy for them.
So that sounds like that's the
psychological preparation portion.
And I don't know that I feel very
confident that a even a trained,
the therapist would be able to really
determine if the medication interactions
and history and physical assessment would
be conducive to a psilocybin therapy.
You know what I mean?
Thank you.
You don't think we could teach on a
singular drugs,
medication interactions and a singular
drugs contraindications?
I think singular drugs,
biological histories,
that would be contraindications.
I'm not saying I don't think it could be
taught.
I'm saying that the training that we go
through as medical providers,
years of physical assessments and history
taking and psychiatric assessments,
a lot of people might present to the
clinic as no,
I've never had this bipolar disorder or
whatever it is.
And it's, you know,
just by somebody saying so doesn't make
it true.
That's why I feel that it would be more
safe.
I mean, are they going to be, you know,
do they really know the parameters of a
safe blood pressure and things like that?
I just,
it seems like a lot to place in the hands
of a therapist in my opinion.
I disagree.
Most assessment is taught within the
first two semesters of nursing school in
terms of those critical ranges,
in terms of being able to assess,
beginning to assess medication
interactions, contraindications.
All of that begins second semester of
nursing school.
So I think it would be feasible to say we
can teach this for just one drug.
Yeah.
Yes.
But you were accepted into nursing school
because you understand and comprehend,
like complex, you know, physical systems.
I'm not saying anything negative about
therapist.
Trust me, I absolutely require them.
I just am saying that the mindset is not
a medical background mindset.
It's different.
So I don't know that they will.
I don't know very many who would really
be very good at that.
Sorry about my dog.
And then I do see some other hands.
So Chris or I,
I think we have Cassandra first.
Cassandra, sorry, I just saw the C Oh, no,
you're good.
No problem.
So is there an assumption, as Reuben said,
Doctor Sutter said in the chat that there
has been a medical clearance or are we
proposing that there does not need to be
a physician clearance prior to getting
treatment even online or you know,
like in what regards?
OK, so let's just say somebody,
if somebody says I'm interested in doing
psilocybin treatment,
are they required to clear it with their
physician or any physi or a physician
prior to starting this whole preparation
process?
Let me at Dominic to clarify.
Yeah, and he did.
He did drop something in the chat.
Good morning.
Must be certified.
Yeah, exactly.
Good morning, everybody.
Yeah, just to clarify,
what we're talking about on this
preparation phase is all of that medical
certification aspect.
So the patient has already gone through a
clinical medical evaluation that they
have one of the qualifying conditions
that has already occurred.
They've been referred into the program.
And then these stages are with the
therapy level now in the the best world
situation and what should be happening
regardless of anything else is all of the
members of the care team.
So that should be the the medical
providers or the clinician, the therapist,
the facilitators,
etcetera should really be working
together,
consulting with each other to ensure that
all of this is happening.
So this stage where we're looking as far
As for preparation really is.
The patient has already gotten cleared
from the medical,
they're going through their preparation.
So the therapeutic,
but that is still going to include some
of that medical interactions and some of
those other information which some of
that should come from the clinical aspect.
And then moving forward with the
administrative as far As for the
facilitator,
which is part of what in the last meeting
had been requested the therapeutic and
that administrative be separated out.
So that's just really what this is going
through.
And Doctor Sutter, I completely agree.
But remember, these are guidelines,
these are not regulations.
So this is what the guiding document as
far as how providers should move forward
with it.
And definitely agree that there should be
that clinical documentation.
But again, these are not requirements.
These are guidance for your best
practices.
Yeah.
So I think put into regulations.
So I think what people are what a couple
of us, Can you hear me?
Yes,
I think what a couple of us are saying on
the call is that the way it's framed
right now is that a psychedelic therapist
would be responsible for assessing
medical medication interaction,
interactions and contraindications.
And that,
that probably should be done by a
physician, that's all.
So sure.
And I think it's just the,
the language utilized is a lot of that
would happen beforehand,
but also during that preparation,
there should be the ongoing discussion of
that.
So for example, a, a great example.
I mean, I, I,
I think we understand what you're saying.
I think we're just suggesting that
perhaps this item would say, you know,
reviewing the, you know,
reviewing the physicians.
Yeah.
But an LCSW would not be able to would
not be able to medically clear someone
for potential serotonin syndrome or you
know,
so maybe in the medical history bullet
point there needs to be some slight
change in.
Yeah.
I think maybe what you just did review is
better than be than do it.
Yeah.
And then I did see in the chat the review
of meds is outside of a scope of practice.
And I do want to clarify that providing
we are providing areas where this would
be within their scope of practice,
this is not an existing function for
anyone to dispense psilocybin outside of
controlled research.
So outside of the scope of practice is
not really a concern because we're gonna
have to provide them with additional
education anyway on psilocybin.
Psilocybin education is broadly not
taught in medical schools or nursing
schools.
So we can review the medical history and
those medication interactions which the
this committee has or patient
qualification and safety has provided
lists of on these topics to try to get as
much access as possible.
There are a bunch of resources in today's
world that can even help to expedite and
to allow more participation.
But I do agree that there should be
clinical oversight.
But it here,
it's just supposed to be they're supposed
to look at their history to make sure
that nothing was missed.
Yeah,
I think the way it's framed now is better
than the way it was framed before.
I think it's good.
I also just had a question about these
committee meetings.
So are some people allowed to chat and
turn on their camera?
And some people are not allowed to chat
and turn on camera.
So the only people we have on camera
generally is going to be the committee
chair and occasionally some DoH folks.
We also generally want to,
as much as we can keep it so that we're
going in order of whoever raises their
hand and then anybody can put anything in
the chat as well.
Yeah,
I for some reason I don't seem to be able
to chat, but I guess I'll figure that out.
Yeah, there,
there are unfortunately occasionally for
some people just yeah,
there there have been folks who haven't
been able to put stuff in the chat.
Unfortunately sometimes there's yeah,
occasionally there will be a thing that
says like some people are outside of the
org,
it's possible they have message related
policies that will not allow them to use
the chat.
So I,
I do see that notification right now.
So that's unfortunately not something we
can change on our end.
But I am going to go to Chris next.
Yeah,
I guess first I'd like to make a request
that people that didn't introduce
themselves,
please introduce themselves before
they're talking.
I see a lot of new faces in here suddenly
and no context as to who you all are.
And beyond that, like I,
I think we've already had this discussion
several times,
but I don't think you know the safety
profile of psilocybin is very good and I
do not think MD's are the proper
clinician to do that evaluation.
I don't think that's necessary.
I think that we can keep the evaluation
done with people that have diagnostic
authority.
And again,
the safety profile of suicide benefit is
very good and we can easily train these
people to do that work.
And then I had something else,
but hopefully it'll come back to me.
I got lost in the conversation.
Thank you.
All right.
And Greg Evans,
I've enabled your mic and you can speak
with me.
Good morning, everybody.
My name is Gregory Evans.
I'm an independent home psychologist and
researcher.
Couple things trying to gather all of my
thoughts because there was lots going on
here and I want to try to speak from a
place of like bridging,
bridging modalities, bridging gaps.
I think one of the things that I wanted
to kind of hatch that Doctor Zurlo
mentioned is that imagine we're in a
pipeline and the pipeline goes through a
singular hole and then it spreads out and
has options.
That singular entry point to the program
has the qualifying condition,
the contraindications, medical readiness,
all of that assessment is complete and
that allows for a broader range of
therapy models that are like like
participant centric.
So if a person enters into the program
with and and I wanna myself here and say
this is how I see it and I see it working
best and none of what I should am saying
should be said as like codified process
because we are in the process of doing
that today.
The if there is a participant that enters
the program with the doctor that is also
a different,
like has different types of therapy in
their practice that has the ability to
qualify them for the program,
which involves all the contraindications.
And I will say,
if we're bringing up serotonin syndrome,
we need to really go back and understand
what the drugs that we're dealing with
are.
We are not dealing with ketamine,
we are not dealing with MDMA.
We are not dealing with any compound that
is known to commonly by itself under like
proper diagnostic protocols trigger
serotonin system syndrome.
The research is out there.
We're gonna get more.
We are in the early stages of
understanding this chemical in general,
but we are not at the beginning.
So if that person wants to stay with that,
that that practitioner all the way
through as their facilitator and their
integration coach and their preparation
team with that, with that single person,
that's a possibility.
There are possibilities where a person
can qualify and then reach out to their
culturally appropriate preparation,
like the person that they want to guide
them through preparation,
sit with them in medicine.
And honey, I just parked to make a little,
have a little chat.
We're gonna go back to your school in
just a minute.
So I, I,
I just think it's really important to
understand that we're not,
there's nothing in the program that is
taking away the medical safety mechanism.
What we're what I think is happening is
that there is a mechanism that is
triggered and authorized.
Once you're in this container,
there are multiple pathways to realize
the process of the therapy.
It's like a,
you get in like it's not the the program
is not for administering medical
psilocybin.
It is a container of therapy that extends
across months.
So if somebody wants to select a
different team or select a broad range of
people to be a part of that team,
those teams need to communicate together.
But I, I hope, I don't know,
I'm going to land it there,
but I hope that makes some sense.
Thank you.
And I do appreciate everyone's input.
I do want to remind everyone this is a
settled issue.
The this committee has already voted and
adopted saying that therapists are OK so
we can't.
I mean, we could try to go back,
but it's not worth our time to go and
hash every single argument that's ever
been had.
So in regards to preparation,
are there any other just questions,
comments, concerns or changes?
I did update that medical history
questions, comments, concerns.
I will let Johnny go back to calling the
roll.
Cool.
All right, Lori, see your hand up.
Yeah, I know we have limited time.
I'm sorry to take up the time,
but can I please clarify a couple things
real quick?
One is,
I know remember it was talked about that
there would be,
and I know this is a moot point at this
time with the therapist thing and I'm
totally on board with the therapist
providing that role, by the way.
I just want to make sure that we are safe
as far as a medical provider reviewing
that person's history and physical
assessment and all that stuff.
As far as like during the administration
though,
I thought we had mentioned that there
would be some kind of medical provider on
site or available during the time of
administration like on call for them.
I thought they had to be on site.
Maybe I was dreaming about this,
but I thought we had talked about that.
I have that question and then I have one
more question and then I'll be quiet.
I know you guys and this is not about
this specifically,
but had been talking with Medicare and
Medicaid about reimbursement and I
wondered if there was any.
I'm just trying to bring this forward to
our executive team in Texas and I I need
that piece of information.
Do we think that insurances are going to
be covering this?
Does anyone have any insight into that?
I would love that information today.
Thank you so much.
So I think, yeah,
Ian can probably speak to that first
question and then Dominic can speak to
the second, I think a bit.
Yeah.
So we had that if you had an inability to
access emergency services and you could
find someone,
you could have someone to administer
emergency medicine on site,
but there was no requirement that they
would have to if they have appropriate
access to emergency services that worked
in that regard.
OK, thank you.
And then this is Dominic.
In regard to the question as far as
insurance and or Medicaid,
we are actually working with HCA to see
what aspects could potentially be covered,
for example, the preparation,
the therapeutic preparation,
the integrative therapy afterwards.
However,
it does appear as though administration
itself of course,
which this is not surprising I think to
any of us because it is schedule one
would not be covered.
However, again that therapeutic sessions,
it looks like it will be,
but there is no definitive answer yet and
I don't know that we're going to have
that anytime in the next month or two for
example.
That may take longer before we have those
answers.
However,
we are continuing to work with regard to
that.
Great, thank you.
And,
and actually I will now Jessica posted in
the chat that if it's an unlicensed
person as a facilitator,
that is correct that they would not be
able to bill to insurance.
And it is part of why it,
we specify in a lot of places the
licensing aspect of this because it's
only going to be those licensed
individuals who are going to be able to
bill.
Individuals who do not have licensure are
not going to be able to bill with regard
to this.
So thank you Jessica for pointing that
out.
I appreciate the assist.
All right.
And oh, let's see,
I saw Ruben Sutter's hand up and.
OK, yeah,
your mic is enabled if you want to unmute.
OK, Unmuted.
Yeah.
It's Ruben Sutter.
I'm an addiction psychiatrist.
I own Sage Neuroscience Center here in
Albuquerque.
Very much in agreement with the safety of
Silas Ivan and.
And you know, these drugs,
given that we're putting this in the
medical context of the medical clearance,
we do have to sort of honor those
pathways.
And,
and I know we've talked about that in
terms of entering medical clearance.
My concern in terms of therapist being
licensed,
providers needing malpractice coverage,
you want to be certain that they're not
being asked to do anything that is out of
their scope of practice.
And so in terms of reviewing medical
history or anything,
that's certainly valid that if they have
the documentation for a medical provider
mid level or otherwise,
which also is perfectly reasonable that
they're just verifying this with the
client rather than, you know,
doing the assessment.
And, and if there's anything different,
I might suggest that then they refer back
to the medical provider largely one,
its scope of practice and 2nd, it,
we're going to have malpractice insurance
and there's going to be risk of liability
here.
And I don't want somebody to be at risk
of doing something that is outside their
scope that would they would expose them.
That's all.
Thank you.
And I, I do want to point that out.
Yes,
if a patient is determined to be
clinically inappropriate,
which means one of their conditions
matches on their list of diagnosis
matches to a list provided,
then the therapist is responsible for
referring them back to their primary care
for provider or other appropriate
treatment.
Ave.
So yes, I completely agree.
Thank you.
All right, I'm next.
We've got Catherine Warnock.
And Catherine, I have enabled your mic.
Hello and good morning.
I'd like to kind of bring us back to
topic, if that's OK.
I feel like we've been talking about a
lot of things that have already been
resolved or are outside of the scope.
I'd like to just kind of mention that I
think that there's two things that are
missing from this list.
And by the way, I'm Catherine Warnock.
I am a psychedelic therapist in Las
Cruces, NM.
Been doing this work for about 5 years.
I think we need to add something about
Matrix making sure that the people have
safety and where they're landing after
the experience.
So set and setting are really critical,
we all know that.
But I think Matrix gets missed a lot.
And Matrix is like,
are we sending them back into a system
that is healthy and that's going to
support this type of a treatment?
So for example,
if I'm working with a client who is
having a is in a domestic abuse situation,
last thing I want to do is send them back
into that with their mind being open and
they're very vulnerable.
Even if it's like the day after or two
days after we need,
there needs to be like plans around where
are they going after the experience.
So I think that's really important.
And then also,
are we going to provide any education
about the the process meaning what
psilocybin does in the brain,
what you know, the neuroplasticity?
Are we going to include any information
about what, you know, what they should?
I mean, yeah,
I see that you have expectations in there,
which is really good.
But just some some education about what
it is, what it does, what it's for,
you know,
just want to mention that as well.
Thank you and thank you Board,
for all the time and effort you put into
this.
This is a thankless paid less job.
So I just want you all to know I
appreciate all of you.
Awesome.
Thanks, Catherine.
And while he's updating that,
we'll go to Brenda.
Hello everyone.
I'm Brenda Burgard.
I'm chair for education training for
psilocybin.
I just want to address that I think with
any type of training you're going to have
a preparation for the clinician and the
patient.
So when the patient is is there in front
of you,
you're explaining to them and you're
having a handout sheet about what to
expect during, before,
during and after preparation.
The preparation is vitally important as a
clinician to give that information to the
patient or client that you're working
with because they are the ones that are
going to decide whether or not to
continue with this program.
There should be an opt out segment in
this too,
because the the the patient should be
able to opt out at any time.
But preparation and education for the
client is vitally important.
So I think whenever we have a,
a patient or a client come to us,
the first things we do is we prepare,
we prepare them for therapy in general.
And this should be really nicely wrapped
up in a nice little package here for
information.
I think that when we do that, the, the,
the client or patient will feel more
comfortable with working with this
medicine.
And another thing I wanted to preface too
is that as, as a therapist myself,
I often ask what types of medications
that they're on,
how long they've been on and how much
they're taking to see if there is any
contraindications of the medication
they're presently taking.
And if I see anything,
I refer them back to their medical
provider to just, you know,
check to make sure that this is
appropriate medication.
So I think when we really get into the
education and training of all of this,
this will be part of the training for the
clinician to prepare the the client or
the patient.
Awesome.
Thanks, Brenda.
And yeah, whenever you're ready.
Perfect.
And then so to kind of sum up the two
last points I heard.
So the general education on The Who,
who out why and how psilocybin and
potential adverse effects,
they should be provided in an easy read
digestible format for patients.
And then the matrix.
But can you provide words because I don't
know why my yeah.
So for matrix,
I would say something like assessment of
suitable matrix,
just making sure that we are that it's
being looked at and that if
accommodations need to be made to they
have to stay with the family member for a
week or somebody that's safe or it's
basically just assessing and then making
accommodations for a suitable and healthy
release into, you know,
an appropriate matrix.
I know that's very wordy,
but I just want to make sure that the
environment and the people that there are
going to are going to be on board.
Like the worst thing you want is somebody
being released and everyone's going to
make fun of them because they had this
treatment.
It's not going to, you know,
it's not going to provide positive
outcomes.
We're trying to do everything for
positive outcomes.
I think you did a good job there, Ian.
Thank you.
But I I stole it from Reuben Sutter and
great, great.
Thanks, Reuben.
All right.
And then we wanted both of those to be
under the psychological preparation.
I think so, yes.
OK, perfect.
All righty.
Any other questions, comments,
concerns TSE Jessica Eden's hand up and
you can unmute when you're ready.
OK, thanks.
And then I just wanted to mention that
like when I mentioned aftercare,
like that's not necessarily integration,
that's like aftercare in that that night
of the day after like emergency,
sort of like, you know,
if they're going to be able to reach out
to the facilitator or the therapist or a
fireside chat, you know,
something like that.
If they need something right there before
their integration session.
It's kind of how I look at that.
This is a different thing.
A different comment or question that I
have is I noticed that you took out
therapist conducting the comprehensive
bio psychosocial assessment and reviews
from that medical history section.
And I'm just wasn't sure where that went
because I think that that is something
that the therapist should be doing.
And that could be shared even with the
facilitator because that's a lot of
history that's taken.
And we would look at that for any sort of
red flags even in the history that we
would want to address.
And then let me know if you need me to
stop.
My other piece would be, oh, shoot,
I'm sorry,
I forgot my train of thought there.
I'll have to come back to it.
No worries, it happened to the best of us.
It is Cinco de Mayo.
My brain already on Margarita time.
This is what it was.
I wonder if the psychedelic therapist
during the process of psychological
preparation should then be determining
and making a recommendation for the
appropriate number of preparation
sessions based on their assessment and
what they're finding.
So like with the minimum of these two,
but then they can make a recommendation
that the that there should be maybe 3 or
4 of them or you know,
whatever they're needing.
So I do like that determines the number
of requisite preparation sessions to
administration.
Is that a good phrasing for everyone?
Right.
I see Chris's hand up.
Chris, you can unmute when you're ready.
I wonder if maybe determines readiness
might be more appropriate rather than
like the way this reads,
it makes you sound like, well,
I based on your history,
I think you should have to do 5
preparation sessions.
But I I don't think that's realistic.
I think, you know,
as they're working together,
maybe readiness is a better measure.
All right, and then cool.
All righty.
Any other questions, comments or concerns?
All right,
then we can go ahead and go on this.
Now,
all those in favour of adopting the
preparation sessions document as proposed,
please raise your hand at this time.
Ian, we didn't,
I don't think we spent a lot of time on
the facilitator section.
Does anyone have any questions,
comments or concerns about the
facilitator session?
You can go ahead and put your hands down
at this time.
All right, Catherine, I see your hand up.
You can unmute.
Yeah.
I'm actually thinking the cultural and
spiritual alignment needs to be in both.
Like,
I'm just thinking we it needs to be all
the way through.
I don't know.
Well,
I went ahead and added it to
psychological preparation.
OK, excuse me And before we go to Chris,
let's see,
I just see Ruben at a couple or a
question in there.
Will there be a minimum expectation for
observation?
We will have to determine that
administration.
All right, and we'll go to Chris.
I think I've brought this up before,
but some things have kind of changed
since then.
It is 60 days before administration.
I I'm not sure that's really appropriate
for for somebody.
I would,
I would think maybe no more than 30 days
and they're probably meeting with their
psychedelic therapist more frequently or
before they're meeting with their
facilitator.
I mean,
hopefully all this is happening in
conjunction,
but I think it might want to be closer to
administration than 60 days.
I believe it's based on Colorado's with
60 days.
I would have to Fact Check my stuff,
but it was either Colorado or Oregon that
had the baseline and we just moved there.
We can change it if you would like,
but 30 days seems a little bit difficult
if we are, you know,
sending them back to to be tapered off of
medication.
And then we need more administration
sessions because they weren't completed
within the last period.
And it was a thing about boundaries.
But I would be OK with changing it to 30
if that's what the committee agrees with.
Let's see.
And I see Gregory Evan's hand up and you
can unmute when you're ready.
Thank you.
I would I would second that 30 days
simply because we're not constraining
people from having a longer period.
We're constraining like the minimum
easiest path.
Also,
I think having wow bugs we're having,
I'm sorry,
totally lost my train of thought.
If we're gonna consider having multiple
sessions,
those secondary sessions shouldn't be
behold to the primary sessions of
constraints.
So if somebody is received like their
primary session and then their team
themselves decide that they should go
back in,
I don't think that they should have to
wait 30 or 60 days.
So I think it should be further
determining clinician team.
Cool.
I went ahead and updated it to 30 days.
And then Dominic.
Yeah, good morning, Ian.
It just seems since we only have a couple
of minutes left in this meeting and there
still seem to be some questions,
what I would recommend at this point is
to go ahead and let people sit with this
until the next meeting before doing a
vote just to ensure that they have enough
time to review it and see if they have
additional questions or, you know,
ideas for some of the changes,
especially with regard to the facilitator
since we've just started reviewing that
portion.
All righty, that sounds good.
I am very busy for the next two weeks.
Does Wednesday the 27th work for the
department and everyone in the committee?
Let's take a look for us Wednesday the
27th should be good do we want to do 9 to
11 for that one just in case sure OK cool
alrighty since we are out of time today,
I do appreciate everyone for taking the
time to be here and share your thoughts
with us.
I appreciate everyone's opinions and just,
you know, taking time out of your day,
it's,
it's something you don't have to do on
something that's so easy to not do.
So I do thank you for being here.
But have a great rest of your week.
Enjoy your Cinco de Mayo and be safe
everyone.
Thank you for your time.